We sigh whenever we're about to come to a standstill
終わりなき旅の途中　立ち止まりそうな時
Owarinaki tabi no tochuu tachidomarisouna toki
While moving on this endless journey.
深いため息こぼす　僕らは
Fukai tameiki kobosu bokura wa
Everytime we lunge for it, it escapes and flies off.
掴みかけてはまた離れていった
Tsukamikaketewa mata hanareteitta
But now, there's nothing to be afraid of
でも今はもう何も恐れることはない
Demo ima wa mou nanimo osoreru koto wa nai
The powerful ties that bind our hearts
心を繋ぐ強い絆は
Kokoro wo tsunagu tsuyoi kizuna wa
Will never come loose.
けして解けはしないさ
Keshite hodoke wa shinai sa
After a lifetime of searching, we finally arrived
探し続けて辿り着いた
Sagashitsuzukete tadoritsuita
Here, where the period lies.
この場所で Period に
Kono basho de piriodo ni
Let's change all our sorrow and rage to power.
悲しみ怒り 力に変えて
Kanashimi ikari chikara ni kaete
Destiny is right within our reach.
運命はすぐそばに
Unmei wa sugu soba ni
It's almost like a maze in here.
まるで  迷路だな
Try not to get lost.
はぐれないよう  気をつけろよ
Okay.
はい
Oww...
痛ぁ…
Are you okay?
大丈夫かい
Sorry.
すみません
What's this?
これは
D-Dynamite!
ダ…ダイナマイト
Seriously?!
うそっ
They're all damp now.
こりゃ完全にしけってんな
Don't worry; they won't explode.
安心しな  爆発はしねぇよ
Come on; get a move on.
グズグズするな
いつ追っ手が来るか分からんのだぞ
We don't know when the enemy will come after us.
Right.
Looks like the blizzard died down.
吹雪は去ったようだな
Get ready.
準備しろ
Aye, sir.
アイ  サー
We're going to take down Kimblee and his
two men from Central when we see an opening.
キンブリーとセントラルから来た部下たち
計３名  隙を見て しとめる
Aye, sir.
アイ  サー
We're going to proceed with the mission with only the men currently present.
作戦はここにいるメンバーのみで行う
Don't tell anyone; not even soldiers from Northern Headquarters.
北方司令部の兵たちにも極秘だ
ちょっ…マイルズ少佐
Hey-
Major Miles!
By "bring down", do you mean you're going to kill them?!
しとめるって  殺すってことか
Of course.
当然だ
I don't approve killing.
殺すのには賛成できない
It's better to seal their abilities and beat information out of them.
術を封じて  情報を吐かせた方がいい
Do you really think he'll tell the truth?
あれが素直に吐くと思うか
It's dangerous to keep him alive.
生かしておくのは危険だ
Then what about his men?
じゃあ  ヤツの部下は
They may also be obeying him without choice after being turned into chimeras!
あいつらも合成獣化されて
しかたなく従ってるだけ
かもしれないじゃないか
You have a point, but the keyword here is "may".
そうだな
だがあくまでも「かもしれない」だ
So you're going to kill them simply based on suspicion?
疑わしいってだけで殺すのか
Same with Lieutenant General Raven! There were plenty of other methods-
レイブン中将の件にしたって
ほかにやり方が…
ブリッグズの掟を忘れるな
Do not forget the law of Briggs.
If you let your guard down, you die.
油断すれば殺られる
Your softness may come back to kill you or one of your friends someday.
君のその甘さが君や仲間の命を
奪うことになるかもしれんのだぞ
We don't need careless men in this land.
うかつ者はこの地にいらん
We're going to get rid of Kimblee and his two men.
キンブリーほか２名
始末させてもらう
なんだかんだで  子供ですね
I guess he's still a kid, after all.
Yeah.
そうだな  この世界で
Trying to settle matters without deaths in this world is a soft idea in itself.
殺さずを貫こうという考えが甘い
But there was a time I was like that, as well.
でも  私にもありましたよ
ああいう時期が
I was, too.
私もだ
You start to understand once you reach this age after living through many battles...
この年になって  いくつかの戦いを
経験すると分かる
...that it's more difficult to keep someone alive rather than killing them.
殺すことより
生かすことの方が難しいとな
The Elric Brothers chose the tougher path.
エルリック兄弟はその困難な方を選んだ
Strange guys, aren't they?
物好きなヤツらですね
Yeah.
But I'm also a bit envious.
だが  少しうらやましくもあるよ
What's this "Rasayana" he writes about?
この「ラサーヤナ」というのは
It's used to describe a miraculous medicine that extends one's lifespan.
長寿を得る霊薬のことだ
I wonder if he's talking about a philosopher's stone?
賢者の石のことかな  えっと
Let's see...
What is this "Aurelian" that "turns all metal to gold,
and transforms old men to adolescents"?
「すべての金属を金に変え
老人を青年に変える」
この「アウレリアン」とは
It's a word for gold.
金を意味する
Most of this talks about immortality and gold.
不老不死と金についてばかりだな
Could it be because Mr. Scar's brother was heavily influenced by Eastern Alchemy from Xing?
この書をかいたスカーさんのお兄さんが
シンの錬丹術に
影響を受けたからですかね
Meaning?
というと
In my country, we refer to the immortal as a "True Being".
シンでは不死の人を真の人
「真人」と呼びます
It literally means "Perfect Being",
but because gold is a perfect metal,
「完全な人」という意味なんですが
金も完全な金属であることから
there are times we refer to
a "True Being" as a "Golden Being".
真人のことを
「金人」と呼ぶこともあります
I see. So a perfect being is a golden being.
なるほど
完全な人は金の人か
Some say we refer to them that way because
the person who introduced alchemy to Xing...
一説には
シンに錬金術を伝えた人物が
...was an immortal man with golden hair and eyes.
金の髪  金の瞳の
不老不死の男だったから
そう呼ばれるようになったとか
Wow...
Golden hair and eyes? Sounds like Ed and Al!
金の髪  金の瞳なんて
エドとアルみたい
Hey guys, come here!
みんな来い  出口だ
I found the exit!
The sun's so bright!
まぶしい
Looks like we were able to get through the mountain.
無事に山を抜けたか
The weather looks nice.
いい天気だ
Let's head to Briggs now while we can.
今のうちにブリッグズへ向かおう
Okay, everyone. Follow me-
よし  お前ら
私について…
Looks like the snow is pretty deep.
結構雪が深いな
(ヘルプミー)
Help me!
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey!
You can ride on my back, little girl.
お嬢ちゃん  背中に乗りな
Help me!
オレたちが踏み固めて道を作るから
We'll make a path through the snow, so you can follow us.
You guys listening?!
Hey! Hey! Hey!
その後から来るといい
Help me!
(ヘルプミー)
We appreciate it.
ありがとう
Hey!
Hey! Help me!!!
(ヘルプミー…)
Is someone there?!
(誰か…)
Al?!
アル
Sir Alphonse?!
アルフォンス様
大変  大変
Oh no, oh no, oh no!
Are you okay, Al?!
アル  大丈夫
助かった…
You saved me...
深みにはまって
I got stuck in a deep spot and ended up getting buried by the snow.
そのまま埋まっちゃったよ
But why are you here, Al?
なんでアルがここにいるの
I crossed the mountain to get here before you guys.
山越えして  先回りしたんだ
You crossed the mountain... in that blizzard?
山越えって  あの吹雪の中を
I get it. Instead of making a detour here, you took a straight path.
なるほどねぇ
迂回せずまっすぐ来たわけか
But why make such a reckless trip?
なぜそんなムチャを…
I have urgent news.
緊急連絡があって
"Urgent news"?
緊急連絡
The Central Army has infiltrated Briggs.
ブリッグズ砦に中央軍が入った
Apparently, Major General Armstrong has been summoned to Central, as well.
アームストロング少将もセントラルに
呼び出しをくらったらしい
So it's dangerous to go there now.
だから  今砦に行くのは危険なんだ
What should we do?
どうする
We can't go back, either.
戻るわけにもいかないしな
You're going to have to find somewhere else to hide out.
どこか  ほかの場所に隠れるしかないよ
Yeah, like where?
どこかって  どこだよ
Follow me.
ついてこい
Where are we going?
どこへ行くんだ
There should be a village by the name of Asbec not too far from here.
ここからそう遠くない場所に
アスベックという村があるはずだ
I've heard rumors my fellow countrymen have taken refuge in the slums there.
そこのスラムに
同胞たちが身を寄せていると
聞いたことがある
An Ishbalan slum, huh?
イシュヴァールのスラムか…
ほかに選択肢はなさそうだな
Doesn't seem like we have much of a choice.
Master, you rock! Let's get going!
さすがだんな  行きやしょう
But is it going to be okay?
でも  大丈夫なの
何が
What is?
Won't Sir Kimblee get suspicious if you disappear all of a sudden?
アルが急にいなくなったら
キンブリーさんに怪しまれない
Nothing to worry about. Brother will keep everything under control.
大丈夫  大丈夫  兄さんが
なんとかしてくれてるから
Three from the third squadron.
第３班  ３名
Five from the fourth squadron.
第４班  ５名
Looks like we're all here.
よし  そろったな
Now, I want you all to begin searching in the districts you've been assigned.
では  それぞれ
担当地区の捜索を開始してくれ
はっ
Yes, sir.
了解
Roger.
Let's move.
行くぞ
Aye, sir.
アイ  サー
Come on, Alphonse.
アルフォンス君
Isn't this where you say "Okay"?
そこは「はい」だろ
But it's really hard to move in this, Edward.
いやしかし  これ
動きづらいよ  エドワード君
That's where I need you to do your best.
そこをなんとかよろしく
Come on, Kimblee's watching.
ほら  キンブリーが見てる
Wait up, Brother!
待ってよ  兄さん
Walk faster.
早く歩け
Hey. Where are Kimblee and company searching?
キンブリーたちはどこの捜索だ
There's a huge mine shaft at the center of the town, right?
町の中心にでかい竪坑があるでしょう
Apparently, they're going to enter that and search the mine.
あそこから入って
坑道を調べるそうです
He said he's only going to take the men he brought from Central because he doesn't trust the soldiers up here.
北の兵は信用できないから
セントラルから連れてきた
部下だけで行くそうです
He must have noticed already.
ヤツめ  気づいたか
We're going to stall them.
先回りだ  竪坑近くに
Secure a position for sniping near the shaft mine.
狙撃のポジションを確保する
はっ
Roger.
Search the entrance to the mine.
坑道の入り口を探しなさい
If you find multiple footprints, there's no doubt.
複数の足跡があれば間違いない
はい
Yes, sir.
Can you do it?
いけるか
At this distance, yes.
この距離なら
What's wrong?
どうした
Edward is...
エドワード君が…
何
What?
Kimblee, shouldn't you leave it to the soldiers from Briggs to search the mines?
キンブリー
坑道を調べるんなら
ブリッグズ兵に任せた方がよくないか
I heard it's a labyrinth down there.
中は相当入り組んでるみたいだし
Seeing as how you went through the effort to persuade me out of it, this must be the place.
あなたがわざわざ
引き止めに来るということは
ここで当たりですね
What are you talking about?
なんのことだ
I just want to capture Scar-
オレはさっさとスカーを…
Or are you trying to buy time to position the sniper?
それとも狙撃手を配置するまでの
時間稼ぎですか
So you noticed?
気づいてたのか
There's so much thirst for blood in the atmosphere; it would be odd not  to notice.
これだけ周りに
殺気が満ちていれば  気づきます
I didn't survive Ishbal for nothing.
だてに  イシュヴァール戦を
生き残ってませんよ
It looks like they're talking about something. What should I do, sir?
何か話してるようですが
どうします
Can you try to adjust your aim on Kimblee?
キンブリーだけを狙えるか
Yes.
はい
Do it. Be very careful.
撃て  慎重にな
Aye, sir.
アイ  サー
That bastard hid himself in snow!
あの野郎
雪で目隠ししやがった
Dammit!
くそ
キンブリー
Kimblee!
Damn you...
この
So you two are chimeras, too, huh?
おっさんたちも合成獣かよ
Shit... I can't see a thing.
にゃろう…なんも見えねぇ
Well, they can't see me either...
まっ  向こうさんも見えないってことで
五分と五分
...so I guess we're even-
おとなしくしていろ
Quit resisting, Fullmetal Alchemist!
鋼の錬金術師
There's no way for you to run since we can track you by scent!
この視界の悪い中では
鼻が利くオレたちからは逃げられんぞ
Shut up!
うっせぇ
Fullmetal!
鋼の
何が起こっている
What's going on?!
どこだ  返事をしろ
Where are you?! Respond!
Is that you, Major Miles?!
マイルズ少佐か  合成獣がいる
There are chimeras here!
And they've been trained to fight in places with low visibility!
視界の悪い場所での戦いに慣れてる
Stay out of the smoke!
雪煙の中入ってくんなよ
Oww...
痛ぇ  ちくしょう  背ぇ縮む…
Dammit... that just made me shorter...
Dynamite?
「DYNAMITE」
We're in a mine, all right!
さっすが鉱山
Don't get too close now!
おっと  近寄るなよ
You do know what these are, right?
これがなんだか分かるよな
Are you stupid?
バカめ
そんなもの
Those are probably too damp to use.
しけってて使いものにならんわ
Do you two know what dynamite is made of?
おっさん方  ダイナマイトの原料を
知ってっか
ニトログリセリン
Nitroglycerine?
ニトログリコール  木くずに…
Nitroglycol, chips of wood, and...
...ammonium nitrate, maybe?
硝酸アンモニウムとか
じゃあ  その硝酸アンモニウムは
Then what's ammonium nitrate made of?
何で出来てんのかなぁ
簡単だ  硝酸とアンモニア…
Easy! Nitric acid and ammonia-
Ammonia?!
アンモニア
The smell!!!
くっさ
なんのにおいですか
What's that smell?!
アンモニア
Ammonia.
鼻が利きすぎるってのも困りもんだな
I guess there's a downside to having too keen a sense of smell.
These guys are toast.
こいつらもう使いもんになんねぇよ
So this is how you're going to act as soon as your hostages are released?
人質の心配がなくなった途端
これですか
Don't know what you're talking about.
なんのことかな
I'm just here to beat all the information you know out of you.
オレはおめぇの知ってることを
洗いざらい吐いてもらおうってだけだ
やれやれ  血の気の多い
Christ, you're so hot-blooded.
Fighting with a young man like yourself during
my convalescence would surely break my bones.
病み上がりで
若者の相手をするのは
骨が折れそうですね
And I don't have time to play with you either.
それに あなたにつきあってる暇もない
I guess I'll be using this, then.
これを使わせてもらいましょうか
He just saved me the trouble of searching for it!
自分から出してくれやがった
He's fast!
速い
Too slow!
遅い
He lost his philosopher's stone,
and his transmutation circle is no longer useable!
賢者の石はなし
錬成陣も使用不可
これで
I-
"I win!"
勝った…と思うでしょう
Is that what you're thinking?
The determination not to kill.
殺さない覚悟
立派なポリシーです
An admirable policy.
But that's just asking for your enemy to take advantage of you during battle.
だが  それは戦場において
つけ込まれる隙になる
今さっきの一瞬にとどめを
You should have killed me at that moment.
刺しておけばよかったものを
That softness is the cause of your defeat.
その甘さがあなたの敗因です
竪坑を落ちたのか…
Did I fall down the mine shaft?
He's so heartless... he even got us into it...
ひでぇ  オレたちまで…
Oww...
痛て…くそっ
Dammit...
Where did Kimblee go...
キンブリーのヤツ  どこへ…
You've got to be kidding me...
うそだろ
Hey!
アル  どうしたの
Al! What's wrong?!
アルフォンス様
Sir Alphonse?!
Al?!
アル
This isn't good.
ヤバい  また引っ張られて…
I'm being drawn again...
What do you mean, "being drawn"?
何  引っ張られてって…
Hey, what's wrong?
どうした  鎧の
Al?
アル
My soul...
魂が…向こうへ…
...is being drawn toward...
アル  アル
Al!
Al?!
His soul is being drawn?
魂が引っ張られる
Sir Alphonse?!
Sir Alphonse! Pull yourself together!
Has this happened before?
お嬢さん  今まで
こんなことがあったのかい
I don't know!
分からない
アルフォンス様
PLACEHOLDER
Sir Alphonse!
Al?
アル  アル  起きて
Wake up, Al!
No...
やだ…アル  アル
Al!
Al!!!
どうしたら…どうしたら
What...
What should I do?!
エド
Ed!
I can't... let her cry over something stupid like this...
こんなんで…
泣かせるわけにはいかねぇよな…
Damn that Kimblee...
くそっ  キンブリーめ…
Yo, Fullmetal.
鋼の  生きてるか
You alive?
お前なんでオレたちを助けた
Why did you save us?
お前の方が重傷じゃねぇか
You're hurt far worse than us.
勘違い…すんなよ…
Don't... get the wrong idea...
I... need someone to pull...
この…腹に刺さってるのを
抜いてくれるヤツが…いないと
...this thing out... of my abdomen.
困るんだよ…
You're asking us to pull that steel frame out of you?
オレたちにその鉄骨を抜けってのか
We're technically enemies, you know.
一応敵なんだぞ
Yeah... please.
頼む…
Well, we weren't ordered to kill you or anything.
まあ  お前を殺せという
命令は出てないしな
Let's see.
どれ
痛っ…
But if we pull that out,
you're going to bleed out in an instant.
でも  お前それ抜いたら
即大量出血であの世逝きだぞ
As soon as it leaves my body... I'm going to seal the wound... before I bleed to death.
抜いた瞬間  大出血する前に
錬金術で…ふさぐ…
なっ  お前  医療方面の
Are you experienced in medical alchemy at all?
錬金術の経験あるのか
I've attempted human transmutation in the past... so I studied the main points.
昔…人体錬成しようとして
ひととおり研究した…
ひととおりって…
"The main points"? I'm pretty sure your organs are shredded to pieces...
これ  たぶん  内臓ズタズタだぞ
キンブリーさんみたいに
If you don't have a philosopher's stone like Sir Kimblee does...
賢者の石でもなけりゃ…
That's why I'm going to use my life instead of a philosopher's stone...
賢者の石の代わりに
オレの命を使う…
What?!
It may shorten my life span by a bit, though...
寿命がちょいと
縮むかもしれねぇけどな…
いいのか
Is that okay?
I don't have the time to dawdle.
迷ってる場合じゃねぇし
If this injury was caused by my softness... then I have to clean up after myself.
自分の甘さが招いた結果なら
ケツは自分でふかなきゃ…な
I don't really get it, but you don't have much time to waste.
何か分からんが
迷ってる暇はないな
I'm pulling it out.
抜くぞ
Do it, please.
抜いてくれ
I need to think of my life as a form of energy...
自分の命を
一種のエネルギー体と考えろ
賢者の石と…同じだ
The same as... a philosopher's stone!
That's right!
そうだ
Right now, I'm nothing more than
a philosopher's stone made out of one soul!
オレは今魂一個分の賢者の石
Think back, and try to remember that feeling!
思い出せ  あのときの感覚を
That feeling...
あの…
...of using...
命を使う…感覚
...life!!!
死んだか
Is he dead?
Don't just write me off like that...
勝手に殺すな…
Oh, it worked?!
成功か
完全に治したわけじゃない
It's not completely healed.
無事な組織をつなぎ合わせて
It's just a temporary measure of linking the undamaged tissues... to stop the bleeding.
とりあえず血を止めただけの
応急処置だ…
Then we need to get you to a doctor!
じゃあ  医者に診せないと
No, I don't have time... for that...
いや  そんな暇ない…
H-Hey!
I need to go after Kimblee...
キンブリーを追わねぇと
...else... everyone will be in danger...
みんなが危…ない…
Geez...
ったく…
アホが
Idiot.
There's no way he can win against him in this state.
こんな状態で戦って
勝ち目ないだろうに
What is it?
なんだ
おっと
Whoa...
A philosopher's stone, huh?
賢者の石か
The one Sir Kimblee had with him, right?
キンブリーさんが持ってたやつだな
「さん」なんて  いらねぇよ
You don't need to refer to that freak as "Sir".
He dragged us into this.
あの変人  オレたちまで
巻き添えにしやがって
You're right.
そうだな  あの野郎とは
I guess that's the last time we see that bastard.
これでおさらばとするか
Yeah.
ここで死んだことにして
People will think we died here, so we're free.
オレたちは自由の身だ
And what should we do about him?
で  こいつはどうする
We can't just let him die.
死なせるわけにはいかねぇだろ
He saved our lives.
オレたちの命の恩人なんだから
Well said.
そうだな  外へ出たら
We need to find a doctor right away
once we get out of here.
真っ先に医者を探さないと
Yeah.
The promise we never made
交わしたはずのない約束が
Kawashita hazu no nai yakasoku ga
yet again
今日も
Kyou mo
tries to snatch our future away from us.
僕らの未来を奪おうとする
Bokura no mirai wo ubaou to suru
Why is it that we can't rejoice
欲しがっていたものを手にしても
Hoshigatteita mono wo te ni shitemo
straight from the heart
素直に
Sunao ni
when we obtain something we've always been after?
うまく笑えないのはなぜだろう
Umaku waraenai nowa nazedarou
The overflowing tears aren't from feebleness or remorse.
あふれる涙は　弱さや後悔じゃない
Afureru namida wo yowasa ya koukai ja nai
They're fragments born from agony.
イタミが生んだカケラで
Itami ga unda kakera de
Of all the moments and destinies,
どんな瞬間だって運命だって
Donna shunkan datte unmei datte
I realized there's one absolute certainty.
ひとつだけ確かなものがあると知った
Hitotsu dake tashika na mono ga aru to shitta
Even if things get tough and I'm at my limit
限界だって困難だって
Genkai datte konnan datte
I refuse to give up.
あきらめたくないよ
Akirametakunaiyo
Please, don't let go.
このまま離さないで
Konomama hanasanaide
I can feel the warmth of your right hand
かたく握りしめた　君の右手のぬくもり
Kataku nigirishimeta kimi no migite no nukumori
where it's tightly joined with my left.
ここにあるから
Koko ni arukara
After breaking the stalemate,
unforeseen ideas and actions open new paths.
こう着した状況を打開し
日本語字幕仕上げ：XIAOBIN
道を開くのは
意外な発想と行動力
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
隠された真実に気づく者が
The one to find the hidden truth obtains the key to victory.
勝利への鍵をつかむ
But that's all a part of the accumulating daily life.
だが  それは
日々の積み重ねあってのこと
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
次回　鋼の錬金術師
Fullmetal  Alchemist
第４２話　『反撃の兆し』
Episode 42, Signs of a Counteroffensive.
The beginning of war.
今  戦争が始まる